Pinelands Folklife Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Field documentation arranged by fieldworker, Field photography descriptions are copied directly from B and C logs via Optical Character Recognition, so errors and abbreviations exist.
  - Christine A. Cartwright
    - Field photography on color slide film
      - Family operation cranberry harvest (wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 28, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-006; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-006; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT 1-3: long shots of the cranberry bogs, showing the raised sand roads made when the bogs were "cut out,: and the reservoir of water from which they are flooded; 4-7, long shots of the cranberry bogs, showing the berries floating on the water in a bog ready for harvesting. In 5, three men are putting together the 12 foot lengths of board used to corral the freshly harvested cranberries; 8-18, shots of equipment used in harvesting. 10 is a gasoline powered water reel used in the wet harvesting. The person using the machine holds onto the metal handle located behind the engine and steers the machine through the bog. The rotation of the cylinder dislodges the berries and they float to the surface of the water where they are corralled and guided to the conveyor belt that lifts them into containers located on the backs of trucks; 8-10, long shots and closeups of "beaters" wheeled through the flooded bogs to knock the berries off the sterns so they will float to the surface of the water; 11, long shot of truck used to load berries from the elevator and take them to the packing house; 12, long shot of elevator that lifts berries from bog to truck; 13, Detail of construction of joint on wooden frame used to "corral" berries, hand made in 15 foot sections (my approximation) by the Micks; 14-17, Bog gates to control the flow of water to and from bogs; 18-20, long shots of the corral spread out in a bog just starting to be harvested.
      - Family operation cranberry harvest (wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 29, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-007; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-007; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT 1-13, towing the corral slowly into a tight semicircle as the berries are harvested. Shots go from long to closeup in numerical order. Francis Mick, seen in al the photos, supervises the water work for all Mick harvests. In 10, Joel Mick, named after his grandfather Mick and son of Francis, is starting to corr al the cranberries. He, like all people working on a flooded bog, wears rubber waders; 14-20, lifting the end sections of the corral as the circle narrow, and checking joints between sections (This bog is being corralled again to catch the remaining berries after an initial harvest.)
      - Family operation cranberry harvest (wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 29, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-008; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-008; 15 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1, Francis and Joel Mick, father and son, moving the corral along the edge of a cranberry bog during harvest, pushing the berries toward the elevator; 2-7, Francis Mick using a small board to sweep cranberries from the edge of the bog into the corral; 8, Henry and Francis Mick on bank; Joel Mick, hired assistant (name unknown), and Dave Kalm (also hired assistant) placing stakes to hold corral in place at bank while berries are harvested by elevator; 9, Joel Mick, hired assistant, and Dave Kalm, as above; 10, Francis and Joel Mick confer about the adjustment of the corral; 11, same caption as #8; 12, Joel Mick places a stake while Francis Mick, board in hand, climbs from the bog; 13-14, Francis Mick stands between a bog gate and the corral. The wooden gate is used to control water flow into the bog. Gates are an integral part of all cranberry bogs; 15, Francis Mick opening a bog gate.
      - Interview with Elisabeth S. (Betsy) Carpenter, Rutgers Cranberry and Blueberry Research Center Penn Place Road, Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 28, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-009; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-009; 10 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1-8, Betsy Carpenter showing location of various cranberry growers lands on topographical maps of the Chatsworth area; 9-10, Betsy Carpenter's office, showing file cabinet with data on cranberry and blueberry pests accumulated by entomologist Philip E. Marrucci; glass-doored cabinet containing full set of back issues of Cranberries Magazine and the journal of the American Cranberry Growers' Association; and original regional cranberry marketing labels framed by Mary Ann Thompson of Vincentown, a local lawyer and conservationist.
      - Cranberry harvest (family operation; wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 29, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-010; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-010; 19 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1, A mossy spot a few yards from the cranberry bogs, where the Shoal Branch of the Wading River feeds the Micks' reservoir for flooding the bogs; 2, Closeup of a cranberry scoop, long used in dry harvesting in the region. The Micks have not used this method for the past ten twenty years; 3-8, Henry Mick demonstrates the use of the old fashioned cranberry hand scoop. Modern water reels, sometimes cal led "egg beaters," can be seen in the background at the edge of a cranberry bog. Note the small range of motion shown in these sequential photos; 9, Francis Mick demonstrates the use of the cranberry scoop, while a young "bogman" helping with the harvest (now dressed to go swimming) watches; 10-12, Francis Mick demonstrates the use of the cranberry scoop; 13-14, Francis Mick stands by one of the family trucks, holding the cranberry scoop. This scoop was probably made in Massachusetts and consists of hard wood with metal tines. Francis is standing on a dike next to a flooded bog; 15, The truck used to carry a case of soda, bottles of cold water, a large picnic cooler for keeping drinks cold, pairs of waders, rope, and sandwiches out to the cranberry bogs during harvest; 16, A second truck, its bed divided into two longitudinal rows of three bins, each about three feet deep, into which the cranberries pour as the elevator's conveyor belt lifts them from the water; 17-19, Dave Kalm, a family friend, clammer, and insurance and real estate agent, climbs to the rim of the truck bins, turns on the elevator's gasoline motor, and guides the flow of the berries into the truck bins with a shovel. He stands atop a truck guiding cranberries into a box as they roll off the conveyor belt that lifts them from the just-harvested bog. The Micks have 6 boxes on each of their trucks and each box holds about 1,000 pounds of cranberries. (There are variations in this box arrangement. Haines and Haines have 2 boxes on each of their trucks while Chatsworth Cranberry Co., Garfield DeMarco's company, guides its cranberries directly into the back of pick-up trucks, no boxes involved. The collection procedure is related to the individual method of cleaning before the berries are shipped to ocean Spray's Bordentown, N.J. plant for processing. The Micks, like most New Jersey growers, are members of the Ocean Spray cooperative.)
      - Cranberry harvest (family operation; wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 29, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-011; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-011; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1-5, Guiding the berries toward the elevator chute, to be lifted from the flooded bog into the truck bed. A small piece of board is being used to push the berries across the water and up onto the conveyor belt; 6-12, Taking the connecting pins out of the cedar boards of the corral, dismantling the corral, and lifting the board sections out of the water to move them to the next bog to be harvested; 13, Francis Mick getting the last sections of the corral out of the harvested bog; 14-15, Stacked sections of the corral, ready to reassemble in the next bog when it has been flooded and the beaters run through to bring the berries to the surface of the water; 16-20, Francis Mick opens the gate between the flooded, harvested bog and the next bog to be harvested, using a crowbar. The gate is simply a set of boards placed securely in the pine frame that lines the tunnel under the sand road between the bogs.
      - Cranberry harvest, Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 29, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-012; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-012; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1-3, Francis Mick opens a water gate between a flooded, harvested cranberry bog and a bog to be flooded for harvesting; 4-5, A drainage ditch between two cranberry bogs, with a water gate where it runs under a sand road between bogs; 6, Francis Mick bends down in the drainage ditch to pick up some sand from the bottom, explaining the necessary soil conditions for cranberry agriculture; 7-8, Francis Mick holds white sand and quartz gravel from the bogs, showing their typical soil type; 9-11, Empty packing crates being mended and checked before loading with cleaned cranberries, Micks' family home and packing house on Chatsworth Road, near G-Hog Wallow; 27GT; 12-14, Henry Mick driving the forklight truck, loading a full box of cranberries onto the cleaning machine which will separate the berries from the leaves and debris mixed in with them when they are taken from the bog; 15-20, The cleaning machine. A box of berries is attached to the raised end of the chute and secured with a heavy chain. Then the box is slowly tipped up by machinery so that the berries pour gradually onto the conveyor belt, which has a rough texture that catches the small wet leaves and bits of grass mixed in with them. The berries drop into the hopper shown in frame 16, while the conveyor belt continues up a second slope and turns under the belt, at right angles to and below the first (frames 17 and 18), catches the berries as they drop from the hopper and carries them into the next room, where they pour through a chute (19) into a packing crate (20)
      - Cleaning and packing of cranberries (Family operation: wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 29, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-013; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-013; 21 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1-2, Berries pouring at a control led rate from a packing crate onto the first conveyor belt; 3-4, Henry Mick rakes still-wet berries to spread them evenly and get the last ones from the box as they pour onto the hopper. From the hopper, they will move up the cleaning belt. He is standing on a special ledge built beside the conveyor belt for this purpose. See PFP-83-CCC-012 for explanation of how this machine works; 5, the flood of berries onto the first conveyor belt: closeup; 6-9, Berries moving along the belts and trays of the cleaning machine; 10, Henry Mick walks into the main room of the packing shed after the box of berries has been fully emptied onto the machine, to position another packing crate be low the chute which drops the clean berries at the end of the machine process; 11, Berries moving toward the final chute after the machine has cleaned them of leaves and grass; 12, Henry Mick watches by the chute to see that the berries are pouring evenly into the box; 13-15, The chute and box, showing residual grass clinging to the last belt and clean berries in the box; 16, The stacked boxes of clean berries harvested that day and the day before, ready for trucking to the Ocean Spray plant for a second cleaning, sorting, and freezing; 17, Haines Mick drives the forklift, with a crate of berries, to the flatbed truck; 18, Haines Mick rests briefly by the loaded truck, fingering the berries gently while he discusses their quality and the year's harvest with Henry Mick and Christine Cartwright. These are berries that must be unloaded from the truck and cleaned. (Haines was named after a family friend, Haines Maxwell. His full name is Haines Maxwell Mick. This site where the packing shed and farm house is located has been owned by the Mick family for over 100 years. The Micks' grandfather bought this farm and the house, although renovated, contains original wooden pegs. The land on which the cranberry bogs are situated was acquired in 1926; 19, Six boxes of just-harvested cranberries arrive at the Micks' packing shed. The berry-laden boxes will be taken off the truck with a forklift. The dock was designed and built by the Mick brothers of poured concrete; 20, foundation of local sandstone on the Mick family home, in which Haines, Henry, and Francis were born, on the same property as the packing house. Similar stones are visible all over the area, and are also used in chimney building.
      - Tabernacle Auction, Tabernacle Township, New Jersey, September 24, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-014; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-014; 16 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        1-16, Crowd shots at G-Tabernacle; 25GT Auction
      - Exterior shots and environs of church, prior to recording evening service; Yardscapes; Sunsets, Browns Mills, New Jersey, October 2, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-015; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-015; 15 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        See PFP-83-RCC-003-005, and Joseph Czarnecki's photos for record of evening service in this church. Also PFP-83-FET1002; 1-6:, Exterior shots, Landmark Baptist Church. G-Browns Mills; 21GT; 7-9, Front steps and door of church, showing inscription scratched in concrete with a stick or something (these photos would have to be judiciously cut). Inscription reads: "For Whoever shall call upon the Name of the Lord shall be saved," Rom. 10:13. (This church places a lot of emphasis on standing on the Word, metaphorically as well as -- here -- literally.); 10-12, Yardscapes G-Brown's Mills; 21GT across the road from the Landmark Baptist Church church, showing the juxtaposition of a new and fairly expensive-looking house surrounded and hidden by trees (with a red fescue grass lawn, nicely rolled and mowed, making the natural vegetation seem more genteel) and an older, smaller home surrounded by flowerbeds and assorted household repair projects. This is about 2 miles off Lakehurst Road, the main drag coming northwest into Brown's Mills, and about 4 miles from the center of town; 13-15, Sunset outside the project house on Route 72, G-Lebanon State Forest; 27GT
      - Interview with Kenneth Yates and Dorothy Yates, Tabernacle Township, New Jersey, October 24, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-016; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-016; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Tabernacle; 25GT; 1-2, The Yateses' living room fireplace, built by Mr. Kenneth Yates and his sons out of old brick from a Philadelphia house. Fried flower arrangement by Mrs. Dorothy Vates on hearth; black hearthrug showing American eagle design popular in the area; 3, Long shot of living room; 4-7, Dried-apple face dolls made by a local dollmaker. Portrayed here are Indian Ann (center), the last Lenni Lenape Indian to live in the Pines, who is buried in Tabernacle Cemetery, with the baskets she used to make and sell door to door; an old woman churning butter; and a farmer wearing the old-fashioned tin bucket strapped around the waist for picking blueberries, in use about twenty years ago and still employed by some pickers today; 8-9, Mr. Kenneth Yates points out a detail of construction he built in the doorframe leading from hallway to living room: the framework is built solidly into the wall itself, extending its support of the upper boards between the celling and the top of the doorway from one supporting stud on one side to another on the other side. Contractors sometimes make less durable doorframes; he generally outdoes the building code on matters of strength and solidity when he builds a house; 10-11, Buck shot by Kenneth Yates, stuffed by a local taxidermist, and mounted in his front hallway. His deer gun rests on the hooves of the deer below the head; 12-20, Kenneth and Dorothy Yates chatting with Christine Cartwright at their dining room table, where the paperwork for their hardware business is done. A portrait of the family when their grown children were young, a painted enlargement of a black and white snapshot, is framed on the wall behind them. Continued on PFP-83-CCC-017
      - Interview with Kenneth Yates and Dorothy Yates, Tabernacle Township, New Jersey, October 24, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-017; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-017; 14 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Tabernacle; 25GT; 1-4; Kenneth and Dorothy Yates chatting with Christine Cartwright over the paperwork for their hardware business, in their dining room at home; 5-14, Shots of tumbling block quilt made by Mrs. Rae Gerber of Tabernacle, and embroideries with the names of all the old families in the township. It was sold by sealed bid to benefit the Tabernacle Historical Society, and the Yateses' bid was the highest. Shown here in its usual place, in the master bedroom of the home. Mrs Yates commented that she loves to look over the names and think about the people they bring to mind.
      - Family operation cranberry harvest (wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 30, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-018; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-018; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1-7, Francis Mick kneels in a bog of ripe cranberries, lifting the vines to check the crop's density and quality; 8, Francis Mick using a cranberry scoop; 9-14, Mr. Joel Mick operating the elevator; 15, Silhouette shot of above; 16-18, The sand road leading to the Micks' bogs from Route 503; 19, A stake marking the location of the drainage ditch in a flooded bog, to prevent accidental slips of foot. Cranberries floating on dark water in a bog already harvested; 20, Portrait of Francis Mick.
      - Family operation cranberry harvest (wet harvest method), Chatsworth, New Jersey, September 29, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-019; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-019; 8 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Chatsworth; 27GT; 1-2, A conference by the elevator prior to beginning to corral the berries in the flooded bog; 3-8, Work in the bog, harvesting. See PFP-83-CCC-007-011 for detailed logs. (These shots taken the day before them, so they are not duplicates, but show the same work processes.)
      - Fishing for bluefish in Kirby's Millpond, Medford, New Jersey, October 6, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-020; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-020; 14 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        1, Mr. Melvin Greenhowe displays a bluefish caught with a live brown cricket in Kirby's Millpond G-Kirby's Mill; 18GT, late in the afternoon; 2-5, Mr. Greenhowe fishing; 6, Two bluefish swimming in a bucket of pond water, waiting to be taken home and frozen for winter use, or fried for dinner; G-Medford; 18GT; 7, Mr. Howard C. Jones Jr. and Sr. running a garden hose through their barnyard to give the geese fresh water; 8-12, Closeups and long shots of the Jones farm's geese and hens and the henhouse.
      - Visit to home of Mrs. Edith Graziano; Sunset shots, Hammonton, New Jersey, September 22, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-021; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-021; 17 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        G-Hammonton; 11GT; 1-3: Mrs. Edith Graziano's kitchen cabinet, showing Catholic holy pictures displayed along with china. Left, Pope John Paul; Center, a French painting of Christ; right center, Madonna and child; far right, modern American painting of Christ; 4-12, Sunset, Route 206 south of G-Tabernacle; 25GT; 13, Sand road off route 206 south of Tabernacle; G-Hammonton; 11GT; 14, Mrs. Edith Graziano's nephew Gene stands by the shrine to Our Lady of Lourdes in the back garden of her home, holding a weaving of blessed palm made by Mrs. Graziano's late husband, Rocky; 15, Closeup of weaving made of blessed palm (Mrs. Graziano did not know if it had a special name); 16, Holy candle at the feet of the Virgin in Mrs. Graziano's garden; 17, Scorched pines off Hwy. 206, south of G-Tabernacle; 25GT.
      - Tabernacle Auction (Thursday - all the rest of our photos are of Saturday auctions), Tabernacle Township, New Jersey, September 22, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-022; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-022; 15 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        1-5, Crowd shots at the Thursday night auction, when household goods are sold much as at local yard sales. G-Tabernacle; 25GT; 6, A Pinelands sweatshirt, with pine trees and moonlight design on back, worn by Mr. Ronny Wiseman of New Gretna and the Tuckahoe Emergency Squad; 7-12, Crowd shots; 13, A woman wearing an apron made and embroidered by a member of her family, cooking in the concession at the Tabernacle auction; 14-15, Closeups of the apron and embroidery.
      - Tabernacle Auction, Tabernacle Township, New Jersey, September 24, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-023; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-023; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        1, A man hoists a cage containing a pair of white angora rabbits over his head, showing them to the audience as bidding opens on them. G-Tabernacle; 25GT auction; 2, A spectator at the auction; 3, A Hereford bull calf is brought into the crowd at the center of the auction for bidding; 4, A white piglet being displayed for bidding; 5, A child's bicycle being displayed for bidding; 6, Looking across the front part of the crowd, from the bleachers toward the auctioneer's platform; 7, Two spectators at the auction; 8, A cage containing a pair of grouse for sale being displayed for bidding; 9, Another piglet; 10, Bidding on potted plants from a nearby nursery; 11, A man lights a cigarette as he watches, from the auctioneer's platform,the bidding on a roll of burlap; 12, A victorious bidder waves his ticket to identify himself by number to the auctioneer's assistant, who will write down the number, the item he bought, and the price he agreed to pay; 13, A stack of white plastic buckets being offered as a single item for bidding; 14, Another bidder waves his numbered ticket for the auctioneer to see as he places a bid; 15. Geese, their bodies lapped in flour sacks to keep them from moving about, while their heads and necks are left free, wait calmly in a corner between stacks of cages containing other birds for sale; 16-18, Mrs. Charlene Harker (right) and an assistant doing bookwork in the auction office; 19, Crowd shot; 20, A man lifts his arm to place a bid on some hens, from the topmost bleacher across the room from the auctioneer.
      - Exterior shots of Kirby's Mill; Farmscape across a soybean field; Cottage industries; The gazebo in Medford, New Jersey, October 6, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CCC-024; Christine A. Cartwright; PFP-83-CCC-024; 16 color film transparencies (35mm slide)